Guide to the Susanna Downie Papers, 1972-1990 AIS.1991.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Susanna Downie Papers
1972-1990
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Downie, Susanna
AIS.1991.23
11.25 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
The papers of Susanna Downie date from 1972 to 1990 and document her activities within the feminist movement and involvement within such organizations. While there are some materials from the national and regional levels, the majority of the files concentrate on the activities of local Pittsburgh organizations. These files are largely administrative in nature and document the development and maintenance of the following organizations in the Pittsburgh Feminist Network: the local National Organization for Women (NOW) chapters, and the Pittsburgh Women's Peace Network. This collection also highlights Downie's role within the Women's Studies Center at the University of Pittsburgh and her related endeavors with the 1987 National Women's Conference in Nairobi, Kenya.
Biography
Susanna Felder Downie was born November 21, 1939 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, the daughter of Robert Rex and Emily Cobb Downie. She married Wilfred Sellars (1912-1989), an American philosopher and professor of philosophy at the University of Pittsburgh.
Susanna Downie was extremely active in the local Pittsburgh-area feminist movement. She served on the editorial board for the Pittsburgh Feminist Network and its publication, which was originally entitled Allegheny Feminist and later renamed the Network News. She was also active in the National Organization for Women (NOW) at both the local and state levels. In the 1970s and 1980s, Downie taught at the Women's Studies Center at the University of Pittsburgh. In conjunction with her position at the Center, she served as the principle editor for the publication Decade of Achievement, 1977-1987: a report on a survey based on the national plan of action for women. The "National Plan of Action" was enacted at the 1977 National Women's Conference which addressed twenty-six areas where women needed to work for advancement within society. Downie served as researcher and editor to evaluate the progress of the action ten years later, which resulted in the publication. Another publication authored by Downie was the book, The marriage and the crisis of Emily Dickinson: a study of the vocabulary and some poems, of the 1860-1865 period. She was also actively involved in the Women's International News Service (WINS) and the Women's Institute for Freedom of the Press (WIFP) and helped organize their 1985 conference in Nairobi, Kenya.
In addition to her academic work, Downie was a passionate advocate in the peace movement. She was a member of local peace organizations Peace Links and the Pittsburgh Women's Peace Network. Downie was also interested in environmental activism and was an ardent developer of sustainable living; for a time she lived in Lakemont, Georgia, and built a geodesic dome house. She later moved to Montana and then later Iowa to "live off the land." Susanna Downie died in Fairfield, Iowa, on November 7, 2003. She was 63 years old.
Scope and Content Notes
The Susanna Downie Papers are organized into eleven series. Each series contains a detailed scope note. The materials largely date from the late 1970s to late 1980s and document her activities within local Pittsburgh-area feminist and peace organizations. The Downie papers are largely administrative files of the local organizations in which she was a member. The collection includes handbooks, conference notes and proceedings, research files, and correspondence.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Susanna Downie Papers, 1972-1990, AIS.1991.23, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Arrangement
Series I. Pittsburgh Feminist Network, 1976-1988
Series II. National Organization for Women, 1973-1989
Series III. Women's Programming on Cable Television, 1982-1983
Series IV. Women's Agenda, 1983-1990
Series V. Women's Studies Center at the University of Pittsburgh, 1973-1990
Series VI. Anti-Nuclear War Activities, 1980-1989
Series VII. National Women's Conference Center (NWCC) Conferences, 1977-1990
Series VIII. National Women's Conference Center (NWCC)1987 Conference Preparation, 1977-1988
Series IX. 1985 Nairobi Conference, 1984-1985
Series X. National Women's Studies Association (NSWA), 1974-1988
Series XI. Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1972-1987
Acquisition Information
Gift of Susanna Downie in 1991.
Women -- United States -- Social conditions; Feminism -- United States; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Nuclear warfare; Personal papers; Women's rights -- United States; University of Pittsburgh; Social action; Women; University of Pittsburgh. Women Studies Program; National Women's Studies Association; Pittsburgh Feminist Network; National Women's Conference Center (National Women's Conference Committee); Women's International News Serivce; Peace Links; National Organization for Women; Downie, Susanna
- Pittsburgh Feminist Network, 1976-1988; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The Pittsburgh Feminist Network materials document Susanna Downie's activities within the Pittsburgh-area feminist movement. More specifically, these files document the transition from the publication Allegheny Feminist to the Network News. The change in publication title was preceded by the development of the Pittsburgh Feminist Network, which sought to organize local feminists and keep them updated on women-related news. The organization sponsored at least two local conferences and eventually dissolved in the mid-1980s. Downie was extremely active in this organization as a founder, member of the editorial board, and council member. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject topic.
  - Allegheny Feminist, 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Network News, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Communications at a Crossroads, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Communications at a Crossroads, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Computer project, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Conference materials, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conference feedback, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conference materials, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Council materials, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Establishment of PFN, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Feminist group listings, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mailing lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs and miscellaneous materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Writers/volunteers/committee lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- National Organization for Women, 1973-1989; II.
  This series focuses primarily on the local Pittsburgh-area chapters of NOW and the Pennsylvania chapter of NOW. More specifically, this section contains the 1980-1981 handbook for the Lawrenceville chapter as well as related file on the handbook and the latest revisions. Also present is the Pennsylvania NOW Times from 1978-1990 and the Pittsburgh-area NOW newsletter from 1978-1988. These publications and handbooks are supplemented by some correspondence and fliers, meeting agendas, and conference materials from 1976-1988 and is arranged alphabetically by subject topic. One of the more extensive files documents the 1981 Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) campaign.
  - Pittsburgh-area Chapter handbook, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous materials, 1976-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ERA campaign, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - ERA campaign, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pittsburgh-area NOW chapters newsletters, 1978-1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Pittsburgh-area NOW chapters newsletters, 1978-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Publicity handbook, ca.1982 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Southwest Council of Pennsylvania, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania NOW, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Pennsylvania conference, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania NOW Times, 1978-1990 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mid-Atlantic conference, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Eastern Region conference, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - National conferences, 1975,1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - National conferences, 1975,1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Women's Programming on Cable Televison, 1982-1983; III.
  This series contains several files on developing programming aimed at women on cable television. These files include publications as well as materials from Pittsburgh's Annual Community Communications Conference. Material in the Women's Programming on Cable Television series dates from 1982-1983 and is arranged chronologically.
  - Administrative files, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Administrative files, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Women's Agenda, IV.
  The materials in this series document the Women's Agenda organization activities in Pennsylvania and some national initiatives. This series focuses on instituting legislative change to improve the situation of women by lobbying for budget increases in childcare and other women's issues. The Women's Agenda series is arranged by date.
  - Conference on older women, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - United Nations Development Fund for Women, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General files, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pennsylvania meetings and conference, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conference and general files, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Board member files and general files, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Employment search for researcher position, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Board member files and general files, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Women's Studies Center at the University of Pittsburgh, 1973-1990; V.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject topic and contains administrative information on the development of the Women's Studies Center at the University of Pittsburgh. This series also contains the Women's Studies Center publication, Synthesis, and newsletter. Related to these files are the materials for the 1987 NWCC Conference (see series VIII). The overlap occurs because Downie worked as researcher at the Women's Studies Center and her primary responsibility was to serve as main researcher and editor for the Decade of Achievement publication for the 1987 NWCC Conference. This publication documented the advancements women had made in business, politics, education, insurance, reproductive rights, employment, domestic abuse awareness, child care, and the ERA.
  - Applications for center director position, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Coordinating committee files, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Courses offered, 1974-1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Karate union, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lectures and research papers, 1972-1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Library resources, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous administrative files, 1976-1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Women's Studies Center Newsletter, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sex bias lawsuit, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Women's studies symposium, Women in the Future, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Synthesis, 1973-1987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Anti-Nuclear War Activities, 1980-1989; VI.
  This series contains several files from the local Peace Links organization and the Pittsburgh Women's Peace Network. These files contain correspondence, event notification, information packets, and administrative files that document the maintenance and development of these organizations from 1983-1988 and is arranged chronologically. In addition to the administrative files, this series includes numerous files of newspaper clippings that describe international affairs, such as security issues concerning Central American and Iran in the summer of 1987 and the Reagan administration's nuclear weapons policies circa 1984.
  - Peace Links correspondence and miscellaneous, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Peace Links correspondence and miscellaneous, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Peace Links correspondence and miscellaneous, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Peace Links correspondence and miscellaneous, 1980-1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Peace Links newsletters, 1984-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Peace Links speaker training manual, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Peace Links information on Soviet women, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Peace Links state outreach, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Women's Peace Network correspondence and miscellaneous files, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Women's Peace Network correspondence and miscellaneous files, 1983-1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Journal and articles on nuclear war, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings on international security, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- National Women's Conference Center (NWCC) Conferences, 1977-1990; VII.
  The 1977 NWCC Conference established a "National Plan of Action" which addressed twenty-six areas where women needed to work for advancements within society. The 1982 conference material was entitled "A New Day" campaign. This campaign sought achievement for women beyond the ERA. Additional files concentrate on coalition building between feminist organizations and ERA groups. The 1987 NWCC Conference material focus on the theme "Decade for Change," which evaluated the progress of women's issues for the twenty-six areas identified during the 1977 conference. The National Women's Conference Center Conferences series includes material from 1977 to 1990 and is arranged chronologically.
  - Conference materials, 1977,1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Conference materials, 1977, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Conference materials and ERA rally, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Conference materials and ERA rally, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Coalition building, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Conference materials, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Women in Media Conference, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Conference materials, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Communications conference, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Decade of Achievement" preliminary drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Decade of Achievement" preliminary drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Decade of Achievement" preliminary drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Decade of Achievement" preliminary drafts, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Conference materials, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Conference materials, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Board minutes, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Decade of Achievement" publication materials, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - "Decade of Achievement" publication materials, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - "Decade of Achievement" publication materials, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Conference miscellaneous, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- National Women's Conference center (NWCC) 1987 Conference Preparation, 1977-1988; VIII.
  The materials found in this series were collected by Downie as she worked as part of a team to evaluate the progress of numerous women's issues since 1977. The files are primarily from 1987 to 1988 and contain publications and other resources used to create summaries of progress. These resources vary in topic from women in business, politics, ERA, abuse awareness, and child care. There are also several administrative files related to conducting the survey and conference. The National Women's Conference Center 1987 Conference Preparation series dates from 1977 to 1988 and is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Arts and women, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Battered women, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Business/credit, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Child care, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Disabled women, 1980-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Election and appointment of women to office, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Election and appointment of women to office, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Employment, 1977-1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Employment, 1977-1988 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Employment, 1977-1988 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - ERA, 1981-1987 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Education, 1979-1987 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Education, 1979-1987 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Health, 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Homemakers, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Insurance, 1985-11987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Media, 1978-1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Media, 1978-1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Minority women, 1985-1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Offenders and older women, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Poverty and welfare, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Rural women, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Sexual assault and sexual preference, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Reproductive rights and health, 1984-1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Decade of Achievement" Survey, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "Decade of Achievement" Survey, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - New plans of action, 1984-1988 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Address lists, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Early intervention resources guide, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- 1985 Nairobi Conference, 1984-1985; IX.
  The material in this series is entirely related to the Nairobi Conference and Downie's role in the Women's International News Service. The files consist of articles, newsletters, conference materials, and pamphlets used to prepare for the conference as well as those distributed at the conference. It also contains administrative and financial records that date from 1984 to 1985 and pertain to planning the conference. The 1985 Nairobi Conference focused on peace and highlighted ten years of action in the women's movement since 1975. This series is arranged alphabetically by document form.
  - Address lists, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Conference packet, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Forms and travel information, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Handout and mailings, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Pre-planning documents, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Pre-planning documents, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Registration and releases, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Reports from conference, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Reports from conference, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Reports from conference, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Survey responses for Nairobi news team, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Women's Decade fund and news team project, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Conference publications, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Conference publications, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Nairobi conference publications, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Nairobi conference publications, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- National Women's Studies Association (NSWA), 1974-1988; X.
  This series documents the annual conference held by the NWSA from 1970 to 1981. There are some additional miscellaneous materials from the mid-1980s. Additionally, this series contains a few research files on sexism and racism in the classroom. There is also material from 1985 Nairobi Conference. The National Women's Studies Association series includes material from 1974 to 1988 and is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - NWSA Conference materials, 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - NWSA Conference materials, 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - NWSA Conference materials, 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1982-1988 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Racism and sexism taskforce, 1974-1980 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Racism and sexism taskforce, 1974-1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1970s-1988; XI.
  The miscellaneous correspondence series covers a variety of feminist issues that was addressed directly by Downie from 1972 to 1987. The majority of these files probably relate to her role in the Pittsburgh Feminist Network, but since it is not definite, these materials have been arranged separately. When possible, the correspondence has been arranged by topic.
  - Abortion rights, 1980-1984 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Employment, 1972-1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - International affairs, 1983, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - KNOW, 1979-1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Politics, 1982-1988 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Sexist violence and pornography, 1980-1987 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Sexuality, 1979-1985 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous topics, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous topics, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous topics, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 18)